so based on what we discussed just now\h
what would be the difference between\h\h
the three types of "practitioners"\h
that the suttas talk about
How would that\hpractically manifest for somebody,
day to day?
So there's faith type, samādhi type\h
and wisdom type, I guess you could call it.
Well, maybe one difference between the faith type\h
and the wisdom type will be that the faith type kind of\h\h
understood to some degree some sort of instruction\h
and he just stick to it regardless of what\h\h
his mind shouts at him. To refine this
understanding you just stick to it.\h
Whereas the wisdom type will have the tendency to\h
try to dig more, like: "What does it actually mean?"\h\h
and "How refined I should be doing that?"
That could be one difference.
Would there be any fixed characteristic, like\h
pleasant or unpleasant for one of them?
I was going to say, maybe they would almost\h
be characterized by the dominating hindrances, basically.\h\h
Well, both of\hthose would be mainly characterized
by their hindrances.\h\h
Probably the samādhi type\h
would be the most pleasant.
So basically with faith type and
wisdom type it could be pleasant or unpleasant.
Probably it would be unpleasant,\h
because having faith doesn't necessarily\h\h
mean that they are not acting out of hindrances.\h
You can be having faith and still be\h\h
inclining more towards the direction of\h
engagement in other ways, whereas the wisdom type\h\h
would be inclining probably towards engagement\h
in form of overthinking things.
So\hwhat would they each have to do?
The wisdom type should refrain\h
from trying to clarify things on their own terms.
Like the thoughts\hor doubts
still present themselves.\h\h
But is that where they would begin? Excuse me?
Is that where they would begin?\h\h
Yes, begin the\hrebalancing of their efforts.
I'm not sure I understand.
Is that\hthe first point where the restraint begins?\h\h
No, obviously the precepts. Yes, because
the wisdom, in and of itself, even if they're\h\h
not aware of it, would come with the implication\h
that if I can just understand this,
it doesn't matter so much...
Yes, unless you have perfected the\h\h
precepts and are living sense-restraint and\h
mindful of your intentions, living in seclusion and\h\h
all of that, that would be the requisite\h
for either of the three types basically.
It's not negotiable. But the thing is, still more\h
often than not they would need to there would\h\h
be a need to refine their understanding of what\h
that training means, especially since\h\h
they will see that the practice is still being\h
unpleasant and they're not clear why it's not\h\h
that they're knowingly kind of... there is\h
some external reason because of which they're\h\h
engaging and they know that once that finishes\h
they'll go back. No. It's like, even if they wanted\h\h
the practice not to be unpleasant they don't\h
know how. That means probably that if they think\h\h
they're keeping all these prerequisites, then they\h
probably need to refine their conception of what\h\h
it means to be sense-restraint, what it means\h
to be not giving into unwholesome states, what\h\h
it means to be in seclusion, all these things.\h
And their task would be then to
rebalance themselves, and like I\h
was saying before, create the\h\h
suitable basis for all these ideas to be\h
seen on the level where they need to be seen.
Which is a mind that has been
deaggated on account of renunciation,\h
not on account of something else. Now, what would the\h
samādhi type have to do? What would be their setback?
A kind of laziness, I guess. Laziness? Well,\h
indulging, I guess if you could say.
Can you indulge in a state of renunciation? Well, no.\h
I mean more like a kind of relaxing let's say.
Is it that they need to give up the samādhi as some people would\hthink? No. But they would need to bring up
things to think about. Well, that too. But\h
what more specifically...\h
A puthujjana can be calm, like super calm. I mean, the\h
Buddha's teachers, reaching the final\h\h
arūpa attainments, just the limit of\h
where self view goes. If just one more\h\h
he would have been extinguished.
Whereas a sotāpanna who actually understands,\h
he might not even be in the first jhāna.
So\hwhy is it that there can be that huge discrepancy?
Because he still delights in that\h
attainment, and to learn how to relinquish that...\h\h
But is it a conscious kind of sensual\h
delight, like is usually happening with
the absorption states that people develop?
Of\hcourse there is delight for anybody who hasn't\h\h
freed themselves from craving, but when you say\hit
that way it would almost sound like it's a\h\h
very obvious sort of infatuation\h
with it or something. But the thing is, you get\h\h
there by giving up this coarse kind of\h
intoxication with anything, pretty much.\h
Well, I guess maybe you're taking that for granted,\h
taking that state to be your result, to be your\h\h
goal of the practice. To take it to be yours.\h
Okay, those are broader kind of\h\h
theoretical terms. But more\h
specifically, what is it that they're\h\h
not seeing basically, let's put it that way.\h
Yes, so you're asking: "What is it that
the puthujjana, who has more samādhi than\h
an arahant, what is it that he doesn't see?
What is the small implication\h
that they will still carry, no matter\h\h
how deeply they go in that\hdirection.\h\h
In general. What's the wrong\h
assumption? The self-view.
Yes, of course. But how would that\h
practically manifest, in that specific example?
Is it that you just tell them?\h
Do you think that you\h\h
could have somebody who has cultivated\h
samādhi and they know that there\h\h
is "no self", do you think\hthat would
automatically make them be an arahant?
Well, I don't know. Because they could\h
just take it as information and then say:
"Oh yeah, of course. I already knew that".
But assuming that that whole yoniso [manasikāra] development
has been there, because otherwise they wouldn't be\h
having that samādhi to begin with...\h\h
Yes, I know. But let's put it this way:\h
imagine you meet that kind of person,
on account of some wrong\h
view - like in the Buddha's time, some fire\h\h
worshipper or something like that, or some brahman\h-
they're living perfectly restraint... Yes.
More than an arahant. More\h
secluded, more withdrawn than an arahant.
What kind of instruction would you give them? For them\h
to actually kind of... Well, that they haven't escaped\h\h
the real of birth. Okay, but what does that mean?\h
Well, that they haven't fundamentally uprooted\h\hbeing.
It's still an activity.
The jhāna is still volutionally produced, so they\h\h
still rely on some sort of - very subtle\h
of course, but still - an activity.
But how do they stop doing that?
They need to contemplate that any activity is a burden.
Any form of activity regardless of how subtle\hit is,
regardless. The whole picture is kind\h
of a burden, regardless. And what would be the\h\h
goal of that discernment? Non-attachment to the\h
pleasure even though those states.
And?
Then it's done. But the thing is,\h
there's something more specific there
that is problematic. Something that they wouldn't be\h
seeing. Somebody who goes all the way\h\h
to neither perception or nonperception, but\h
as puthujjana. And now you're asking: "What is it that they\h\h
are not seeing?" That you can get something.
What is it that they take for\h
granted, let's say, as important?\h\h
Well, that thing itself, that lifestyle.
Why is it that the fetter of sīlabbata-parāmāsa wouldn't\h
be overcome in that? Because sīlabbata-parāmāsa\h\h
doesn't just mean the rites and rituals that we\h
often say, it's the right virtue, the right\h\h
duties of being secluded, restraining\h
your speech and all this stuff that would factually\h\h
lead to these peaceful states. Is it like, "I" have\h
to do it? Yes, but... I have to keep\h\h
those things, I have to engage? The thing is, if you\h
just tell: "Stop thinking 'I am this'"
they can easily be kind of: "Oh,\h
yeah yeah, okay okay." Because they have already\h\h
developed a degree of giving up, so it's like they\h
can even think that that's what they're already\h\h
doing, so you have to phrase it in more accurate\h
terms that would directly cut through their\h\h
assumption and the thing that they're emphasizing.\h
And I think I actually already mentioned it a few\h\h
times, but it seems it didn't fully make the\h
connection. Is it to make them recognize\h\h
that this state is dependently arisen?
Yes, but let's not put the emphasis on\hthe state.\h
That even this state that they have developed\h
is dependent on this lifestyle, that taking for\h\h
granted the given state of affairs, the way that\h
it is, basically. Like a healthy body for example.\h\h
Yes, that would bring them closer to it. So then\h
they don't see impermanence, fundamentally.\h\h
Well, they see impermanence in regard to everything else\h
except this. They have reached that state by\h\h
seeing the impermanence of sensual pleasures,\h
because the suttas describe these ascetics,\h\h
not even during the Buddha's time but before, they\hwould factually reach the Brahma\h\h
realm and so on, because they developed the\h
understanding of sensuality as impermanent.
And they would be preaching\h
that as their dhamma, but it would stop there.
They would not see the impermanence of that too, but\h
now the point is, that's just an answer\h\h
that somebody can read in a sutta and they just say:\h
"Oh yeah, they need to see that state too as\himpermanent."
But what I'm saying is, what is it that\hyou could point them to,
to really\h\h
make sure that their understanding is impermanent.
Because, again, they could just assimilate that\h\h
view and say: "Oh yeah, okay, of course\h
it's impermanent." Yes, so then it\h\h
stays on the level of information. So\h
how would you tell them: "If you\h\h
understood it as impermanent, if you actually\h
understood it is impermanent, what would happen?
That would be complete dispassion. Which would mean that...? That they\hdon't care whether that state even comes back or not.
Excactly. So that's what I was trying to\h
get to. So they would still be carrying\h\h
the implication that, even if they think they're\h
free from suffering, because the suttas would say,\h\h
like Bāhiya... he was exactly in that position, where\h
it was probably unthinkable that he would have\h\h
been thinking that unless he had developed his\h
mind in these ways.
But unless they recognize that actually it doesn't matter... Because\hyou can have all the views, like: "Oh yeah, it's\h\h
impermanent, and it's like this and it's like that",\h
but as long as there's that implication that "only\h\h
if I have this, will I be in the right kind of\h
position, will I be practicing rightly", to that\h\h
extent you haven't understood that this is not\h
worth holding on to and it's not where the purity\h\h
comes from. And for as long as that's the case,\h
you will also have sīlabbata-parāmāsa, because\h\h
your peace will depend - like you said - on the\h
lifestyle that produced and that enables the state, so\h\h
it's not that that virtue that they were keeping
- that would give rise to this - was wrong, and they\h\h
should stop doing it. It's the fact that if they\h
recognize that a peaceful mind isn't what
freedom from suffering is, isn't what nibbāna\h
is, if they were to understand that, they would keep\h\h
the virtue with a completely different attitude.\h
They would keep the virtue without any fear of\h\h
what would happen if they don't keep the virtue.\h
Because they're not afraid of the agitated mind.\h\h
But if their notion of peace is intrinsically\h
bound up with this pure state that they have\h\h
cultivated, inevitably they will be afraid of\h
what will happen if they give up all of the\h\h
right training that they've been cultivating, and\h
let's say not fully start engaging in sensuality\h\h
or something, but just go back to eight precepts, and live in a crowded environment, which again, an\h\h
arahant could also do if there's some reason for\h
it or some accident or something, and they just\h\h
can't live in the monastery anymore;
if all these prerequisites were to be\h\h
destroyed and the state were to be destroyed, they\h
would feel like they lost their freedom, because\h\h
it was bound up with with all this. And that's what it means to say that\h\h
it's dependently arisen, but the problem is,
nowadays these ideas are so kind of...
When the Buddha said that it was revolutionary, so when somebody\hhears that they would be forced to think about\hit\h
It's like: "What does he mean\h
with that?" But nowadays you just say say that to someone\h\h
and whoever has any inkling of spirituality would\h
have heard that before and they would just say\hthat
they might even have cultivated the state by\h
practicing something like that, so they will\h\hthink:
"Of course, yes, of\hcourse it's dependently arisen."
But no, accurately speaking,
if you were to actually understand that,\h
then they would realize: "Actually, sometimes\h\h
I'm even prioritizing things that are necessary\h
for this calm to come about, but are not fully\h\h
indispensable to be free from greed, aversion and\h
delusion", like avoiding all talk, avoiding all
speech. The Buddha didn't do that.\h
Avoiding criticizing others
and avoiding discussions,\hengaging in in-depth\h\h
conversations about dhamma. The Buddha didn't\h
avoid those things, because he understood that even\h\h
when the mind would get slightly...  fall\h
back basically from the state of samādhi that\h\h
depends on seclusion, he wouldn't suffer on account\h
of this. But somebody who whose sense of identity\h\h
literally depends on having that withdrawn\h
mind all the time, they would feel like: "Oh yeah,\h\h
I always need to be living this super tight\h
lifestyle of not just - again - the precepts, but\h\h
like all of these other layers of withdrawal\h
added to it. And that's why then the Buddhist\h\h
told Maha Kassapa that: "just come back and\h
and live in the palace, because you don't need\h\h
the seclusion" and\hliving in that cave
where he was.
Like: "Your job is done." Yes, he had to\h
walk up this huge hill just to reach\h\h
that cave where he was living, completely\h
withdrawn from people and then he said:\h\h
"It's for the example." To give a good example\h
to next generations and for his pleasant abiding\h\h
here and now, that he would continue to do it,\h
because he realized: "Inevitably, even being\h\h
an arahant, if we were to go back to that more\h
engaged lifestyle, and meeting people all the\h\h
time and all this stuff, that pleasant abiding\h
would deteriorate. But it didn't say:\h
"Oh I won't do it because I need this." No, so in\h
his case it was just a preference, but ...
but if some reason he got sick and he had to not\h
live up there anymore and just live\h\h
in a more crowded place he wouldn't suffer even\h
if then his samādhi deteriorates.
Yes, so there would be no fear\h
as you mentioned earlier, and that sometimes indeed\h\h
also the suttas say, like: "Free from greed, hatred\h
and delusion, and fear."
Because if there's anything that you hold on to, even if it's\h
the things that are beneficial for the practice,\h\h
to that extent you will suffer. It's a better\h
attachment than all the others, because this one
takes you closer to nibbāna rather than away from\h
it, but if you just stay there, it's kind of like:\h\h
you just moved all the way to\h
the crossing point and then you just stay there.\h\h
You could have just... But no. You stay there.
And\hthen you die. And if nobody tells you:\h\h
"Wait, no. Just one step more forward, don't\h
stop", then there is no indication that...
you're not suffering anymore, so why
would you keep trying to do anything more?
But there's this sutta somewhere, I think in the Samyutta [Nikāya], where there's\hthis sick monk, basically dying I think
and the Buddha comes and he asks him how he's\h
doing. He's like "I'm not doing very\h\h
well." And he says "Okay well I hope you're at\h
least free from remorse." And he said "No,\h
I'm not free from remorse." And he said "Why?"\h
"Well, because I fell away from the thing." so are\h\h
So are you saying that that monk did not even have the right view,\hor could someone with the right view...?
No, there could still be some slight emphasis of...
Because there's still conceit and\h\h
identification with the aggregates, so they could\h
still have a sense that they need to have\h\h
peaceful mind in order to... Of course, they\h
would see through it.
That's the difference. If they were\h
just to practice long enough it would become clear\h\h
that they have to apply the same principle. They just wouldn't be able to hold\h\h
on to it to anywhere near the same degree as\h
somebody who doesn't have the right view.
That's why it does say that once\h
they develop it well enough, then they need to\h\h
contemplate that that's also impermanent.
Not because they are like the other person,\h\h
implying that it's actually eternal, like those\h
brahmas. They would actually have the view like:
"No, this is [eternal]", overdoing the kind of\hfinding safety in it. They know that there\his,\h
like as to suttas say, somebody accomplished in view is\h
incapable of taking any sankhara as permanent, any\h\h
sankhara as pleasant and any dhamma as self. So\h
they cannot have the view that it's\h\h
otherwise, but there can still be... just by\h
not being fully clear that it's not just\h\h
impermanent, but as it says: "It's like a dart, a boil,\h
an arrow, it's a calamity, a disaster", then they\h\h
aren't fully turned away from\h
the entire extent of the aggregates, basically.
So back to your question of\h
what does a faith type\h\h
and a wisdom type and a samādhi type, what do\h
they have to do in order to overcome\h\h
the corresponding shortcomings.\h
Would a simple answer to that be\h\h
to try to understand what the other two\h
types are and to try to emulate them?\h\h
In a way that could be a good way
to look at it.
Actually, there's even that sutta\h
where it says: somebody who is accomplished in\h\h
discernment should go and ask somebody who is\h
accomplished in calming, how to calm the mind.\h
Somebody who is accomplished in\hcalming should go and ask somebody [who is accomplished in discernment]...
It says: "How should you regard sakharas in order to develop discernment", basically.\h
That would be the way to fill out the\h
things that they haven't sufficiently cultivated.\h\h
So in the case of the wisdom type, it would\h
just be like: How do I keep myself in\h\h
check not to drift away into some sort of random\h
distractions, even if they seem justified,\h
like thinking about dhamma.
Or the faith type, distractions of - who knows - helping\h\h
the teacher or something. Just overly kind of like:
"Let me take care of this? Do you want me to\h\h
renew the whole kuti? Do you want a new bathroom?
Then for the samādhi type, it would just be actively
clarifying the nature of\h\h
their experience in such a way that even when\h
they're not at peace, they still wouldn't suffer.\h\h
To take away the emphasis from\h
the peace and see: "How can I\h\h
not suffer even amidst suffering?",
so that even if I were to just - again - completely
live in this crowded environment, in a hospital\h
or something, that even then I wouldn't suffer.
How could I develop such understanding\h\h
that I don't suffer even when I'm going\h
around left and right like this other guy does?